okay in this video I am going to talk
about the user defined data types let's
see first what is water the user defined
data type user defined data drive is
nothing but the data type which is
defined on the other type status already
even defined in the sequel server now
why do you be require a user different
different data type in the first place
you require a user different database
type in the first place because of all
the simple reason that in case if you
are using
the variable type again and again which
has a same length and a same data type
or the same data type is better to
create a user-defined data type and use
the it everywhere
why do you or why what do you like to
you create it in the first place the
reason is very simple what happens is
that suppose if you have a name you have
defined a name that is where care for T
in every table maybe you have employed
table maybe a customer table and many
other tables like that now you are
defining a name that is basically a name
of the customer name of the employee and
you have a Val care for tea now suppose
this being a standard now suppose if you
wanted to change this thing to maybe 45
or maybe 30 whatever it was lesser in
length or a makes more in a length no
you would have to change it in every
place everywhere in all the tables
wherever you have mentioned it been
whatever places you have specified it
even in the store procedures wherever
you have used it how if you had used a
user-defined data type in that place you
would need to change that data type only
in one place and it will get changed it
will get affected in all the places
wherever you are using it
as simple as that that is the main
reason for using a user-defined data
type it gives you ability to create
tables and store procedure that are more
uniform in the data type and can be
easily modified okay now let's start
creating a data type okay it is really
simple easily use the create create type
bbo is the schema name you will be using
a schema name and the name of the data
type what do you want to create and from
what data type you want to create
now suppose they for example create type
dbo name from VAR car 14 what it does is
basically it creates a data type known
as named as name from Vark are 40 means
it would be Barker 40 type
instead of using every time now for the
name for a first name last name back at
40 I could use it that name that I
defined at variable as name I just come
to it and I will show it to you how it
is done
let's first create these data types we
this is first creating a data type with
a data type name for vodka for tea and
I'm going to execute it
under it has executed now again I am
creating an another data type creating
another type from the data type
date/time here it is again
executing it
this time I have created a DDD
which is their type date time I can I
would be using it wherever I want I
could always use it at duty
usually you don't use it for the date
time for the very simple reason because
date time is always going to be fixed it
rate it doesn't may actually change any
time oh you cannot do any motivation for
date time but this is just for making it
all the thing uniform rather than
actually
really creating the date okay now here
is one more never define will see the
status usually use a straight up like a
bit for true and false whether the
employee is actually still working in
their organization or not
were they not working whether the
product is available or not bid remember
though it is known as a bit this still
takes one bite executed
let's go to the other
now as you know all the most of the
tables if you know that have addresses
were delivery having a state so we can
have a B state always defined here in a
case suppose if I wanted to I did not
want to have the abbreviation of the
state I wanted to have a state full name
I would only have to modify this type
here with a cap should 2025 whatever or
what whatever I wanted to do and it will
get actually affected in all the tables
and procedure wherever I am using it
here it is another one I can also
specify would not null here exactly or I
can specify at the inside a table or in
the whenever I am using it in the
procedure or wherever the places I'm
using it right now in this case I have
used it but do not null right here now
this gives you a less flexibility when
you say not null here right here then
you cannot make it null inside the table
now in this case I can use it like that
or I can still take it as a not null and
using by using in that table because I
have not made it normally okay here's
one more
I mean creative one more data type I'm
just creating a few just to show it to
you how actually is going to work
usually you would be creating a lot of
user-defined data types in a very large
database you will have to first forget
out what you are going to do when we
would offer designing our tables here is
one of the thing
here is the table that uses the
user defined data type as you can see
I've created a table dbo testing amp and
not null in this case I will use the
needed I've got it actually taking from
the sequel server and the rest I am
using a user-defined data type as you
can see F name was name that I already
defined up a limb again name again I am
using the same thing so I have in case
now I can because I have not defined it
as null I can make one of them null and
the other one not null if I defined it
as a not null up there then the thing is
that I cannot actually make it not null
or make it null as you can see
yeah I've defined us dbo dot name for
the work our 40 I'm not defined it as
not null so I can use it as null or not
null depending upon the situation
wherever I want to use it we clear in
what you want to do and then only you
start doing it until I you may later I
have to have a lot of problems with a
user-defined enter name now here they
address be address again address one we
address one you see that it's actually
making a things easier and suppose if I
wanted to change the address size little
bit to a longer size longer this thing I
have to get changed at one place and I
have to get all the other type and it
would get actually reflected here
automatically I don't have to change it
everywhere in that play table that's the
point
actually having for having the
user-defined data type now let's go to
the V city-states and this thing okay
understood
oh that's actually execute and create
this table
now the table has been created
let's check it out
maradona
we'll help testing
check it out the table
theoria we have this table created as
you can see okay and there is a name and
other things here let's move it a little
bit up and as you can see we have a
user-defined data tab actually being
used in the table in the first place it
is theory as it is named and the rest
are all user-defined it all types of so
you can take it out the length here also
okay now that you have got a little bit
hang of what are the user-defined data
pipe will go move a little bit further
know basically suppose if I want to I
want to drop the type I created with
many other types do I want to drop it
will not allow me to drop this data type
that I have created for a simple reason
because our table is using it as you can
see it has thrown up the error message
okay and which shows that the data type
is being used okay we referenced by an
object testing as a table name if there
are other obvious it will be listed here
you cannot draw if I want to drop that
data type I have dropped all that
objects before or I have to alter data
objects before most most probably I
would be always ordering add objects
before dropping a data type I cannot
drop though all of objects it doesn't
make sense
now let's create one more data type okay
to show you what exactly how it works
now I am creating a type already numb
okay and I will execute it
okay there we go it has created the type
and a lien I am going to create one more
table and I am going to use going to use
that ID num to create an ID in the table
creating a user after creating okay now
all the table has been created using a
user-defined data type now I am going to
insert a few rows into their table let's
say I inserted three o's
now I do have heroes into the devil
now suppose if I wanted to grow up the
data type I would have a first order
that tables test to where I have
inserted three rows and alter the column
ID with a very cat well not null exactly
the same length as of the data type all
contain a different length but usually
as it was defined as Bearcat 12 here I
can change it to the Barker 12 and then
drop the data type that I have created
in here
now let's run it
I'm going to alter the table later I am
going to drop that pipe that I have
already created to show you today how it
works before actually going through
let's run it once this thing once again
be confirming that this cannot be
dropped as you can see it cannot be
dropped it is being referenced by the
table do no I'm going to order a table
too and I'm going to execute it
and once the table being people has been
altered then I can drop their type
because now it is no moving reference by
that table of course if it was even
reference by are some other objects then
still you have to actually order that
those objects also may be stored
procedure maybe other tables we are able
being reference in this case there this
is the only table it is being reference
to and I have altered that table and I
am going to now execute this thing and
you will see that the type has been
dropped
now let's create one more type again
let's create another type user-defined
area type that this is known in my state
this time I'm going to use it in the
stored procedure rather than that table
here it goes
okay I will just take it up whether
there are there a procedure exists if an
accessory I want to drop it
okay because it doesn't excel well and
good now I'm going to create a stored
procedure who say is create Ock DV oh
that is schema name by default my
procedure state my this is the way I am
using a user-defined data type again
here as you can see and I am going to
select it as this thing the variable
that is being passed actually is the
input variable is user-defined it
arrived state has been defined as my
state which was created before that
user-defined data type and I am going to
actually create this procedure by
executing it
and it has created a procedure now let's
actually execute this procedure and
let's see it
it should work and then we will try to
drop that user-defined data type my
state and see what exactly it comes to
as you can see all the rows for the
state CA has been listed now let's drop
the user-defined datatype and let's see
what happens
it should throw up the error message
that is being referenced by the object
my procedure as you can see it has
already given it it is being referenced
by the object my procedure you cannot
drop the data type now let's go and
alter the stored procedure that is
actually created and removed at
reference to that user-defined data type
here it is I altered it
as you can see character to it has been
defined and it has been altered
no drop type
again there's executed
there we go well what completed
create type
now this time I'm going to show you how
to create a type user-defined data type
of a table rather than just a single
type here is it I'm going to create type
computers TTD at a table I am going to
actually use a scale this thing and I am
going to create a table now we are going
to use at people for little bit other
technical functions let's execute it
now I show you why we actually okay it
already exists no problem okay this is
the create type already exist I don't
want to actually recreate it okay okay
now let's actually drop this table would
exist if it doesn't exist but I'm good
when I'm good now we are going to create
the people create table computer skills
okay now we have created a table with a
computer skills and we are going to
insert some few rows into this table and
then we are going to use the
user-defined table
and all here it is
we are going to create a procedure first
which is going to it says create
procedure dbo
user insert computer skills in the skill
table as computer TT read only this is
actually the data type we have defined
up compared to TD type at a table these
are the two fields of this type of a
table and this is varied but we actually
be creating the
data type as of the scale table which
will be of the computed DD type
read-only as insert computer skills
skill type skill group select skill
skill up from skill table go now that
table will be passed on from now to the
create procedure and that would be
inserted into computer skills
now hold on for a minute I just show it
to you
this is a table net is known as a create
computer skills we are be able to insert
the rows okay
now firstly it says insert computer
skills the skill type these are the
field name select this thing and this
would be coming from the stored
procedure up as a parameter we passed
now
now we are going to insert hold hold add
people we are going to create a table
right as a computer TT type to hold or
data this data may be coming from some
other place okay but before you
understand this thing then we insert
this thing into the hold skill table
data type that has been created as this
thing as computer didi type okay and I
can insert rows and then I can execute
this dbo insert computer skills
procedure and I can pass the whole
discreet table right there but remember
that thing you cannot actually separate
things separate them if you separate
them it will not work you have to
execute all these three together declare
it and insert it and execute it
otherwise it doesn't create the inserts
and it will give you an error now let's
execute it
now you can see it has inserted many
many of the rows in a single disdain and
one one one row and there is a seven
room
the seventh row has been inserted with
the lost execute state when these six
are from this thing seven more from here
first seven one one rows and that was
the seven rows that I been actually
showing affected was executed is from
the insert the computer skills this is
the stored procedure and I will just
show it to you we are it is go on into
it is gone into the computer skills
table okay now I am going to show you
the contents of the computer skill table
and this will once you see we will end
the session here
this is select
execute
and as you can see all the seven rows
have been actually jumped up into this
table this was how actually you can use
a user-defined data type you can you
create a table of the type you can use a
user-defined enough it has many many
many many positive things you can do
with it it is also being used in the
data modeling tools like Earvin power
designer er studios and many others
basically they are known as data
dictionary they're okay I'll just send
it here for the user-defined datatype